Hello. Okay, welcome
slashwelcome back
to this next phase of activity.
Right now, technically, we're in the
cohort 8
first meeting back, continuing with
basically reviewing the first half of
the book and talking about chapter 6,
which as I joked a little bit before,
it's kind of like an alternative chapter
1. And we can we can talk about why that
might be. And just in terms of what is
going to be upcoming for the next two
months,
Andrew Pasha, who's a very
wise and and studied facilitator, and I
will be alternating. So basically on
Thursdays there's a meeting at 15 and 22
UTC
and cohort 8 and 9 are in effect and
they they switch times but people tend
to join at the time zone that works for
them rather than the cohort. So, like
right now we're in this 15 UTC
and then next week at 15 UTC that'll be
technically cohort 9 looking at chapter
1. So, feel free to join either or both
of the live sessions or you can check
back after the live session and and
watch the video recording.
Um
there are
a lot of ways to participate in the
textbook group.
It's more than could fill a day. So
figure out how much time and in what
ways you want to actively infer this
topic. The learning can look like
classical undergrad type studying of the
textbook, annotating it, all of that,
doing things by yourself. however you
like to do it, working in your personal
knowledge management spaces all the way
on through aesthetic expression, uh,
writing code. And there's also a lot of
collaborative ways that people can
contribute to this textbook group and to
the open-source active inference
ecosystem as well.
And that will continue to hopefully get
drawn out over the coming weeks. But
we're going to be working on code.
There's many code examples that are not
discussed in the textbook, but we do
want to have some of the code examples
that exactly recapitulate some of the
textbook examples. Uh so in the
contribute to the textbook group,
there's there's different ideas that
that people have listed over the time.
And uh one way that we structure the
meetings and also just give ways for
people who are here or not here to
participate is through this questions
table. So there's questions for each
chapter that people have written. So
sometimes they're kind of like just
confirmatory like what did what did this
mean or what what do they mean by that
here? Sometimes they're more advanced
like how do these ideas relate to these
ideas or how does this equation get
reached? Um or just open-ended
questions. And so when we're starting a
a chapter discussion, it it could tend
to look like just, you know, seeing
who's there, seeing what's top of mind
for anyone who wants to share a
reflection that's grounded in the focus
topics or or chapter.
Uh, and just see what questions and and
uh ideas arise right there from whoever
wants to begin. And then
uh we can go to the questions table and
we can either look at the interesting
questions that people have upvoted
or we could go to new questions or if
there's any questions that people who
are in this current phase of activity
have submitted then this is a good way
to kind of like get it down in writing
and it's really fun to read through this
kind of work and write down okay I don't
understand what they mean here and then
like that goes from being a known
unknown and then you reduce your
uncertainty and then now you know you
know and that's active inference itself.
So it's a fun way to kind of have a
little media as the message type
experience with the materials.
So, all of that being said, there's a
ton more to explore in this KOD document
that I'm not going to go into right now,
but explore around unfold different
lists
and uh
let us just jump right into it.
We're
talking today about the first half of
the book. So chapters 1 through five and
also chapter six.
So does anyone just want to start with
any general t takes or questions or or
comments on the structure of the first
and second half of the book or on
chapter 6 or or I can add a note on
that. But is there anything just that
that anybody wants to kind of begin with
or that that that they want to start
with? Yeah, Andreas and then anyone else
who raises their hand.
>> Yeah, thank you Daniel. Um, yeah, so
like I've said, um, I've read the whole
book and I've participated in the last,
um, you know, half year. Uh, and I
wanted to understand the math. Um, and I
felt I just didn't understand the math.
But I have a PhD in math, so I should be
able to understand it, I hope. Uh so uh
a few weeks ago I just sat down and I
wor realized and there was a very nice
video um I I'll have to say who the
author was. It just said it much more
clearly than the book and then I kind of
sorted out. It's like five or six lines
uh I could show how I understand it and
then maybe you could see if I got it
right or not. But it's not in the book.
Uh so this is for the variational free
energy. So if I could at some point I
would like to show that. That sounds
good. Let's sort of just stay at least
one foot in the book, but continue.
>> Yeah. So, this is the foot that's not in
the book basically like to see where is
this in the book? I can't find it.
>> Yeah. The book is not intended to be
comprehensive
of the whole field. It's it's a kind of
like extended length paper that gives
many chances to to explore further. So,
I mean totally feel free. Well, but so
the but the point is is that I read a
200page book. It did not have the five
lines of math that I wanted to see, you
know. So I would like to, you know, I
don't have to show it, but but I think
it would save everybody uh it would just
be helpful for people to see like, yeah,
where is, you know, where's the math,
you know, right? So uh that's what I
have to offer. I guess that's what I'm
interested in.
Yeah, great. When when we come to it,
the people have have done different
walkthroughs of different levels of
depth on the free energy
um equations.
>> I think also maybe I'll just try to hook
in with Jonathan.
Well, this is from the first part of the
book. I think that's the point. I don't
know if this is the right day for this,
but uh but I know that Jonathan Shock in
South Africa, he's interested, I think,
to talk about the math. And Octopus had
a learning group on the math. I don't
know who else would be interested in the
math, but that's what I'm interested in.
Yeah,
great. any any other just any other
things people want to just share what
what parts they want to focus on overall
or or just a general question or or I
can kind of make a remark on just the
chapter six and chapter one.
Yeah, I think what what you're uh
hitting at, Andrew, is uh kind of going
from from Baze theorem to active
inference, right? And there just seems
to be this kind of leap where, okay, I
think I've got Bay
down. I shouldn't say down, but I I'm
understanding it enough. And then we get
it. It just seems like it gets
complicated in a hurry. And then in the
textbook there's the the three
variations of the equation where it
talks about um complexity minus accuracy
and energy minus entropy. I I'm guessing
that those equations are all
saying the same thing but just from a
different lens. Is that or a different
perspective? Is that right
Steph? And then yes we can explore that.
All
right. Might might be a slightly
different topic or point of view here.
Um I am interested in
getting the
getting the intuitive understanding of
the connection between
thermodynamic
entropy and and like a information
entropy
and where those things are.
I don't think equivalent is the right
word, but
that's the main transformation that
I'm I'm wrestling with.
>> Great.
Yeah, these these are these are all
important
areas. Andress.
>> Yeah, I was on mute. I guess I didn't.
Um, uh, with regard to who who spoke be
who who who are the two people who spoke
just so I get the names right.
>> Uh, Mark Roberg.
>> Mark. And then uh,
>> so Mark I think talked about the math.
And it turns out that the book is um
it really like it just the real math
just starts with one line that uh
explains what the free energy is and
then you just
scoot some terms around and then you get
that it's the sum of two um it's the sum
of two differences. There's a sensory
difference and there's a conceptual
difference and you minimize both. So
you're minimizing the the discrepancy in
the outer world and you're minimizing
this discrepancy in your inner world
like your model how you know compared to
the reality it's supposed to approximate
and it's called an approximation which
really is not very helpful because it's
not an approximation. It's your inner
model of what the world is like. So it's
the Q let's say you're comparing the Q
and the P. And so when you see that math
then the whole entropy thing can make
sense. That's it's important to see
those five lines that I would like to
show. Um
yeah lot lot to say here. Also it's
important to note like free energy
variational basian inference isn't
introduced in this textbook. There's
several decades of work on that topic
and active inference is kind of about
bringing that into a unifying cognitive
cybernetic type framework. But if you
have a variational autoenccoder, not not
to jump, you know, too technically too
quick, but a variational autoenccoder
that's doing end to end, whether it's an
image coming in and a classification
going out or it's sense data coming in
and robot action going out, it's already
doing active inference.
So this is kind of like a quick
introductory
textbook through that area.
But
a lot of the work on the more analytical
formalism and on the especially the
codebased aspects is happening outside
the textbook. So let let us not only see
it as a detriment that this or that
isn't included in the textbook. That's a
discrepancy between maybe someone's
expectations of a textbook and what the
document actually is.
But then that's either something that is
happening outside of the textbook or
it's an opportunity for future
contributions like Sanjie's um future
book. So I'll just make a general
comment on the the structure here and
then also about this bay to active
inference question.
Um so the book has two halves. There's
chapter one through five which they talk
about in the beginning of the book as
kind of being the epistemic. So that's
more of like the learning and theory.
And then chapters really six through
nine are a little bit more practical
and model specific. They have a lot of
details about what certain kinds of
generative models look like and
citations to where those can be found in
more detail. And chapter 10 is kind of
like a summary. So chapter 1 and 10 are
like these bookends that are a little
bit more big picture. One is
introductory. 10 is a little bit more
synthetic.
And then chapter six is kind of a fun
alternate chapter one for for those
people who like a little bit more
practical orientation or they have
experience with systems engineering or
other sort of analytic methods because
chapter 6 is the recipe for building a
generative model. So it's kind of a
process of structured thinking of which
there are other structured processes as
well. So again where somebody sees like
this should have been this way or that
you know it's like that's your method
that that that can coexist
chapter 6 gives this method of four
steps that in one way or another
basically have to come into play to have
the active inference generative model.
So that we're going to return to that
again and again like these questions
either have been asked to yield a full
generative model
or they haven't at which point it's not
complete. Um and then about bay and
active inference and where does this
like free energy value come into play?
This is the figure 1.2. two. And this is
a motif that structures chapters 2 and
three which are on this low road
bottomup kind of builders engineer
um can't understand what I haven't built
existentialist in the sense of like
constructivist building things and this
and then on the top down from the high
road is more of this generic physics of
cognitive systems like information
geometry and free energy principle and
then where they meet is active inference
and that's like described in chapter 4.
Um how do you get from B theorem to
free energy? Well, when you write down
some kind of model that's going to do
updating,
if you're working with enough compute
power or a small enough problem to do
exact basian calculation, you can just
do that. You can just exactly calculate
the basian updating. However, there's a
wider range of problems where it takes
too much resources or it's not plausible
to actually compute over certain aspects
of B theorem. And so that's where
approximate basian computing and the
whole probably approximately correct
frameworks come into play.
And then
there are several flavors of heristics
and all these different things but one
of the key ones is this variational
inference
again which has existed for decades.
It's known as the evidence lower bound
and and we can go into more detail but
like it just those are some of just
putting puzzle pieces out on on the
table. Those are some of the things that
that come into play.
And it isn't like this textbook or even
this last five to 15 years of research
invented any of these topics.
So it's more like a composition
of these topics which you can go down
different avenues to understand their
intrinsic coherence.
But then we bring them on the table and
we look for their relational coherence
in the context of
cognitive systems modeling.
But cognitive systems modeling including
a continuum from something that's like
trivially inert to kind of classical and
repetitive like a metronome
on through more sophisticated cognitive
phenomena.
all the emotion, attention,
anticipation, these kinds of things.
So, just trying to to give like many
first little pins in. Um, so anyone want
to just add add a comment or or go to a
Yeah, Steph, go for it.
>> This is a question
on the uh on the motif, the image. Um
um
do you typically consider this from the
individual perspective or do you also
consider this motif from a like a a
group of individuals
um surprise minimization
uh point of view? Like is there scale
and variance to bringing this to
multiple levels of networks or do you
should this
typically be viewed as a an individual
in infer
like um or or do you do you ever do
collective
many individuals but you look at them as
one individual inferring?
Yeah, this is a an important question
for the collective behavioral studies
and for multi-agent systems. So I think
a good recent paper again it's this is
now 3 years on from the textbook. So
there's things that just are outside the
scope of the textbook and and happened
later but I'll put this one in the chat.
This is I think is a a a great one that
that talks about that. Um
two two ways to explore that. First is
through the partition
even one is understood to consist of a
partitioned number of states. So even if
we're talking about one
thing
we're thinking of that one thing in
terms of three even at the most coar
grained. Basically it's blanket states
the incoming perception like and the
outgoing action like and then the
internal cognitive like. So even the
sort of
diatic agent niche is already a
four-fold representation with a blanket.
So that that's one way to go to say okay
well one is already multiple and and
that accords with our understanding of
you know all systems being composite
already and then kind of working up
where let's just say you have agent
environments
you can compose
and and sum the values across multiple
agents.
Now whether that summary statistic is
available to the lower level agents
that's a design decision you could enact
or not and then whether
available or only sort of with this sort
of with a supervisor like a simulation
runner who gets this summary now whether
that summary statistic is meaningful or
relevant or actionable or better at
being used than the estimates of the
individuals. Those again are are that's
another level of of
questions.
But the I mean again there's there's so
many ways to go with this but the idea
would be that the the composability
of the graphical models
supports
kind of zooming in and partitioning
a collective
down. and then also building more
flexibly up.
>> Yeah, thank you.
>> But this book does not go into any
multi-agent aspects at all.
It just focuses on on the sort of single
organism,
but it it it makes some notes. Like if
we're looking at um you know a nervous
system example like in chapter 5, it's
like yeah you you could zoom in and you
could you could go make a cellular level
model but like again that is the sort of
connection between more general
hierarchical nested complex systems
biology approaches
and this is like okay and here's a way
where you can compose those models and
then that also kind of connects to some
more recent work like with the
reormalization group and everything.
Anyone can can raise their hand or or
write a question.
These chapter six qu questions
are
great questions to think about. Um
they they set up instead of taking the
sort of chapter one literature review
approach. This starts to read again more
like a set of steps you can follow to do
a given modeling process.
And whether you only keep this at the
level of sketched out on paper or
whether you take it on through one of
the multiple possible ways to execute
this code.
Seeing this as recipe creation that gets
prepared or not, like there's recipes
that you can write out that you can't
cook or there's recipes you could cook
but you don't have the time or the
resources to. It gives it a lot more of
a a pragmatic
basis in what modelers do. Like active
inference isn't just an oracle
dis dispensing
opinions on different phenomena.
It's a modeling framework that modelers
use
to explore different hypotheses
about systems of interest. So the first
question
which system are we modeling? It's like
the generic form of active inference is
not making reference to any particular
system at all.
So there's nothing about any particular
system or any aspect of any system
that on a first order invalidates
anything about the generic formulation.
So
th this is kind of like I mean again a
lot of ways to to to explore this but
like
starting with a system of interest and
then exploring the interfaces that has a
lot in common with systems modeling and
stock and flow modeling and other ways
of doing systems modeling. This is just
one that that continues on and connects
to a lot of effective software.
Um, but yeah, do we want to continue
through these questions or is there some
other question from the first half
of the book or from chapter six that
that people would rather look to?
Daniel, I I feel like I could ask you
you questions and I don't want to be
rude uh with the other members here.
Um my question in in an act of inference
sense would be do you consider there
being an end like a goal for yourself
relative to the constituents in the room
or what is achieved here? And it's kind
of more of a personal question like what
is what is the textbook review
and this type of what what would you
prefer to see come out of this? Um, is
this a room where one just has the floor
to ask questions
um where you can bounce around or is it
to be that there are so many cohorts
going on and it makes sense to be in
sequential order to to the book? Um,
like what is your preference to get
things out of it? because otherwise I
would I would start to to to be I could
be quite selfish and I don't want to be
>> yeah I I'll look to see what other
people want to add. Like for me it it
gives a time boxed opportunity to go
over important material the many many
many times which some of us may want to
or feel like we need to go over it. like
using it to have one foot in the book,
rereading an important
text and connecting it to more recent
and other resources
is a valuable
exercise.
I like to see when
in their own motivation and way people
who are activated to either show up and
learn and participate in open science
and and be a part of the community and
then also realize that there there's
more contributions than not
to to create code to do all these
things. like week by week people could
be bringing lists of questions and short
blog posts or research that they're
working on along the way
and I mean yeah I can I can add more but
but this is about as with everything at
the institute opportunities for people
who want to learn and apply active
inference to connect with other people
who want to do the same
rapidly reduce their uncertainty see
about what resources already exist.
>> Good. Thank you.
Okay.
Yeah. She
need the
>> Yeah, these these are great videos by
Shamil Chandaria.
I'm amazed the book doesn't include the
math. I I hear you.
Doesn't start by defining free energy
and reorganizing the terms. Well,
chapter one is just a background
chapter.
Chapter two basically does the minimum
walk to get to free energy.
starting with the base theorem
and starting with the exact base
and then basically saying well
you can't always do exact base.
Sometimes you need to make an
approximation or you need to have your
own internal model of another process.
So Andrew, I'm I'm I'm Q is not
arbitrary as the book implies. It it's
it is selected arbitrarily by
the modeler of the agent.
That doesn't mean ungrounded or
haphazardly per se, but it's it's
selected at will by fiat regardless of
of what the external world is.
Mark
Thank you. Um, yeah, thanks for going
over these steps here. Um, it I've read
the book and you at least that part of
the book and several tutorials. Um, I
think Smith was the first author, Ryan
Smith was the first author on the 2022
tutorial which which I think had helpful
elements in it as well. Um it seems like
there is a lot that is made of uh the
idea that we we can't do exact bays and
that we can't have an exact uh
I don't I guess it's not the likelihood
there there's there's a term that is
it's the uh the Q right that is not that
we can't have or no P one of the values
is not so we we get into this where the
variational idea is introduced.
But I I think that if I'm right the
active inference that I mean that's not
necessarily the main point that's a
point but the main point is that there
is a way to uh minimize that divergence
and and that's what the active that's
like the the essence of active inference
is minimizing that that difference right
but I guess the step that I'm confused
on is the fact that well there there is
a difference between what
the true posterior that's what it is
right there's a difference between the
true posterior and our our approximation
of it
I I don't know if that's a coherent
question
yeah there's a lot of important pieces
there so let's think about some
landscape
I I always find it interesting that
biologists
when they're talking about fitness they
talk about increasing fitness
or like a computer scientist might talk
about increasing reward. So that's like
hill climbing algorithms. So there's
gradients that you can follow to
increase
uh on that landscape and and to get up
to to more rewarding state um or a model
that fits better. And then there's this
dual way to look at it like flipping
that landscape and going downhill.
Because if you think about surprise as
being
basically inversely correlated with
model fit, then minimizing surprise is
having a better fitting model. If you
were minimally surprised by the next
observation coming in, you would have
the most evidence for the model. um
you'd be you know least surprising would
be if you perfectly predicted what was
about to happen you would have the least
possible surprise.
Okay. So there's first this core duality
between having a model that fits better
which you also want to penalize by not
overfitting but just leaving that second
piece aside for now. You want to have a
model that fits better, which is
equivalent to being less surprised.
Now, which way to go? Do you want to
ratchet up how well your model fits or
do you want to try to ratchet down how
well or how much surprise you're getting
from observations? Those are equivalent
processes.
And what variational inference does is
with a distribution that you control Q
which is the the approximator
distribution.
You can make this
decomposition
where
the evidence term like the o how likely
overall is this fogyny?
How likely overall is it that Bitcoin is
exactly this price? Those questions are
actually like you could argue whether
they're hard or easy, but
they're not needed to calculate a
gradient with this left term. So that's
one of the key things that allows you to
if you're working with that surprise
bounding approximation
to follow a gradient that actually has a
very simple structure and can be
computed and incrementally optimized
without needing to like worry about your
absolute elevation so to speak
cuz you just have to test. Okay. Should
I adjust the knob this way or that way?
Not like how loud is it overall?
>> So, how is Q under our control? I think
that's what you said, right?
>> Yeah.
>> This is great, by the way. Thank you.
So
Q is the distribution that that the
agent is proposing. You know,
I don't want to copy it every single
time, but we're talking about a map of a
real system. So we're not saying like
this is what the bird is doing or
something. It's like we're modeling the
bird this way or we're choosing to build
an agent this way or something like
that. Um now
the world could be handing observations
through any number of mechanisms. It
could be a neural network. It could be a
lava lamp. It could be radioactive
decay. It could be running through a
list. It could be so the the way that
the world generates those observations
could be any numbers of way. But by
having a distribution that's controlled
like I'm going to model those incoming
values with a Gaussian distribution and
then I'm going to shift the Gaussian
move the mean and then I'm going to
adjust the standard deviation like make
it wider or thinner. So it's like I have
two knobs on my Gaussian.
That's the one I control. And then I'm
going to kind of like do this etch a
sketch
controlling those two knobs to make the
best fitting approximation Gaussian for
whatever data are coming in. And again,
the data coming in could be like, you
know, 333 9999 3 I3399 and you'd get all
these secondary like should I should I
have a big Gaussian that fits over both
or should I do a tight one and then flip
it. So there's all these statistics
questions that come into play. But the
big picture is you have a welltempered
etch sketch
Q
that you know the properties of and
control the properties of and got to
choose completely
and then because the agent is making
updates
only on Q and action
only updating it's it's it's taking the
external observation in
but not modifying observations like the
thumb isn't on the scale
but by saying okay well now I'm going to
change the world change the mind those
are the two options I'm going to have a
unified
energybased model minimization process
where to some extent I'm going to either
be updating beliefs on Q you know which
but it could be beliefs about action as
well but not going to have my thumb on
the scale and I'm not going to engage
with the possibility of of direct
telekinesis.
Like only through action will the
generative process out there in the
world be modified.
But I'm going to adjust my sensemaking
frames
andor my action selection beliefs
based upon the the pointlike
observations that I'm getting in.
that gives this like wellont controlled
setting
where even if the the process out in the
world were were changing how it were
being generated
still the model of the agent would be
kind of like well typed
that's a good explanation so I just and
I don't want to dominate the
conversation here but I just want to
follow up here Q includes obviously
predictions
um and you were talking about precision
of those predictions when you were
talking about uh the type of
distribution right am I going to have a
a wide or am I going to have a narrow
that that reads as precision is that
right and and that precision is also a
prediction right so so I'm making these
and so you would you see that as
separate or you see that as just kind of
all inclusive and then finally it seems
like the action
is also
embedded in the model if that's the
right way to describe it. So it's so so
the model Q has sort of I mean you can
kind of bake everything into Q is that
right?
Yes. Like the agent is the joint
distribution
of all of those things. It's a joint
distribution over perception, cognition
and action.
And so doing optimization on that whole
joint distribution like th that's the
variables you need to represent in code
to have the agents is its whole joint
distribution.
Those that's
the joint distribution that constitute
the generative model. And so that could
have if that could have
just um it could be like a spike like
belief. So infinite precision
moving just exact beliefs around. Or you
could add another parameter to have uh
more of a a two parameter belief moving
around like the mean and the variance
like the Gaussian. Or you could have all
of these compositions of different
variables.
Again, you get into this secondary
question of model selection like what is
the relative model adequacy or what are
the resource costs associated with these
different models or is there a fair way
to reward them for fitting well but
penalizing having more parameters
that's like the bay information
criterion those are sort of secondary
questions arising
but whatever joint distribution you have
is the generative model for for the
agent Andre
Yes. Uh I had a question about um
equation 2.5 which you showed earlier
the three equations
and then um
>> okay
>> you hear me?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. 2.5 and then the middle one it's
about complexity and accuracy. I'm
wondering how to derive that. That's the
one I couldn't do.
Sure.
>> Yeah.
This was um
Yeah. Did Did you look at Well, you
looked at Jonathan Shock's material.
>> Not yet. I I just want to if you go to
the equation.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> Here was here was Yakob, I believe,
wrote these.
Also just just as a sort of note, I'm
I'm currently vibe theorem proving with
lean
and exploring some some more distilled
representations.
>> Uhhuh.
>> So I so you know for to for anyone who
who wants
>> So this is very good.
>> But yeah,
>> where where are these notes? Where are
they available?
>> Um it's in the the canvas for equation
2.5.
>> I see. You open these up and then it
gives derivations. And so this is
there's a there's a page on equations.
Is that right?
>> Yeah. And the equations page has like
the latte code. Um
>> Okay, good.
>> Yeah. And then it's in here. I I I know
it's kind of scrolled away in a little
canvas, but not not everything can be on
the the main table. And and also again,
this is like, you know, 30 to 70 years.
These are stable derivations. This isn't
intended to be new ground in the book.
It's just reviewing that that free
energy functional has these different
compositions possible and then
>> yeah I wanted to find this so I didn't
know this. Okay, thank you. That's very
helpful.
>> Yeah and and there's like there's
statistics textbooks we we we could
probably link to connect
that might go into a little bit more
detail but but I found Yakob's uh moves
here
quite useful.
Very good.
>> Yeah.
>> And I think Nick had a question in the
chat. I don't know if it was answered
already, but
>> is Q the same policy as RL? Um,
>> no. So there's uh
policy.
If you're talking about a belief
distribution over policies,
yes,
but Q more generally is just used to
refer to any belief distribution.
There's Q-learning
in machine learning
which is um also kind of gets
gets close but as with many machine
learning things and and reward learning
like there's this another reward um
distribution layered in that we don't
really engage with here directly but if
you um look at the Q-learning learning.
You see a lot of com uh a lot of uh
concordances with with how belief uh
beliefs about state transitions work
here. Basically, a reward is associated
with state-to-state transitions.
So you have you know you say okay I'm in
this um grid world and the transition
from here to here's
my reward value on that in in the
approach that's taken like in the POMDP
in the textbook the B matrix is just the
state transition matrix so that's just
beliefs about policy conditioned beliefs
about state transitions
then expected states
lead to expected outcomes
which then get evaluated in terms of
pragmatic value and how well those
expected outcomes would align with
preferences.
So that's how there's this kind of
Q-learning like dynamic but again it's
not the variational Q but it doesn't
involve this trained reward function. It
just uses latent state transition
matrix.
What observations do I expect those
states to transition to to admit?
How would I feel about those
observations if I were to get them
instead of if I take this action, what
states do I expect it to go to? And what
reward do I assign or receive from that
transition?
How do you reward a machine?
Keep it running. Update software
Lee. Yeah.
Oh, wait. Unmute and then go for it.
>> Okay. Sorry. So, I have a questions
about the Mac blanket.
>> Yes. So like in on in the first step we
have to define the system right
as uh like um one of the way to define
system is to um yeah one of the way to
define the system is to focus or to
define the mark of blanket.
It makes me think about like a language
model. We can consider it as an entity
living in a text word which it can only
access to a text and it can only take
action as generating text. So
can we consider the text itself the mark
of blanket or is the environment or is
both?
>> Yeah, good question. So this this uh
just about the LLM specifically this
this
>> paper kind of starts to explore that and
there's been later exploration.
Um there's kind of two ways to address
this question of Markov blankets when it
comes to real systems. The first one is
like interface design and just thinking
empirically what are the inputs and the
outputs. So in that sense just what are
the what is the model receiving
your prompt what is it outputting that
language. So you just think about this
as like API calls.
So just do a first approximation. That's
the blanket. And then also there's
blanket discovery methods
that you can use to explore like what
in a little bit of a semi or
unsupervised way.
What are underlying
what are the underlying things that seem
to be sending messages? But when it
comes to to to
modeling
pretty much just think what observations
are coming in for that agent what is
coming out and if you have fully
enumerated that you describe the Marov
blanket.
>> Yeah. Then
well I wonder then the
because um like I think uh my intuition
is just that a language model should
have a generative model of a language
environment. But if we consider the
language that it get as input and output
as it blanket then it cannot access to
the real environment that is uh um human
user human customer. Is that right?
And it can only model the real
environments as in the real human
interactions by um um processing the
information it gets from the text.
>> Well, it's like I'm only getting your
audio and visual and I'm only sending
you audio and visual.
>> Yeah. So similarly an LLM might only
receive audio
or just text.
But
>> yes, but like um as a an active
inference agents,
one should uh one should model the
environments outside of its direct
perception. Right?
And for the language model for the LRM
it means it needs to
simulate the environment outside the
text. Is that right?
Just like I want to simulate
like information from you. I I can only
access your image, your videos, your
audio, but I I want to maybe think about
your thought.
>> Yeah, there's there's a lot of ways to
go. I'd say if evolution were acting on
a given agent to exist
within a niche, then there starts to be
an aboutness of its predictions about
the world outside.
But if it's just whimsically placed in
an environment,
its predictions might be totally
irrelevant.
So it doesn't need to be doing it like
again the express
the the space of models you can express
includes the nonsensical ones. Like you
could have an LLM that's trained on
language one getting input from language
2.
So like it's the internal model that it
is a map of maps could map very well or
not well to another situation but maybe
sketch it out or or
make some open- source code or write it
out a little bit more fully
and and we can explore it like there's
so many things that it's just hard to
convey through real time but the beauty
is that we can diagram it and actually
code it.
>> Yeah. I I somewhat understand what you
mean. Yeah. Thank you.
>> Cool. Okay. So, um yeah, I
I hope people can use the the the rhythm
of what we do here to
learn on their own trajectories.
If it just the more preparation and
work up front that people do like the
more fun it is. Coming with written
questions or coming with something that
you worked through to share
is awesome. So I hope that that people
scan over what is already existing.
if you want, you know, if you don't have
access, request access to to make edits,
right? Write questions and and um I'm
looking forward to
where we go and and and if you show up
later time, you'll enjoy Andrew's
facilitation.
Otherwise, just look at the meeting page
and kind of
please look at what we're going to be at
least trying to connect with and have
some quotes or some specific pieces that
we can go to. But certainly, as it's now
been like three and a half years since
the textbook,
we increasingly
draw on other resources outside of the
book.
And uh
there are other learning and and coding
and development experiences at the
institute and elsewhere.
So if somebody just like wants to be
that zero to one and start up a math
group or start up another project or
work on some other focus like that's all
great. Not everything has to happen
within the textbook group. Not
everything has to happen within the
institute.
Awesome. Yeah, Steph, go for it.
>> Daniel, question. Um, I
want to start a group to help
um
to do let's see what's where's the the
best place to start a group or to like
um
demonstrate interest in a particular
direction.
Yeah, I'd say go to welcome.active
inference.institute. That'll kind of
just take you to this living document to
our main page. And then project
preparation.
If you want to submit a project and have
it visible to others, then just
completing this form
will will get you on and then that and
then people can um it it basically will
be included in the activities
and then the activities page has all of
these projects.
>> Cool. All right. Thank you. See you all.
Thanks for the chat. Bye.
Thanks so much.